A Guide to the Papers of the Albemarle County Medical Society, 1933-2002
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Government of ACMS: Constitution and By-laws 1945, 2 D, 1 pamphlet (Box-folder 07-003)
- Government of ACMS: Incorporation 1951, 6 D (Box-folder 07-004)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws 1967, 4 D (Box-folder 07-005)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws 1967-70, 1 D (Box-folder 07-006)
- Government of ACMS: Constitution and By-laws 1972, 1 D (Box-folder 07-007)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws and nonprofit organization 1974, 7 D (Box-folder 07-008)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws and incorporation 1975, 10 D (Box-folder 07-009)
- Government of ACMS: Constitution and By-laws 1979, 3 D (Box-folder 07-010)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws 1984, 3 D (Box-folder 07-011)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws 1985, 8 D (Box-folder 07-012)
- Government of ACMS: Articles of Incorporation and By-laws 1986, 7 D, 2 pamphlets (Box-folder 07-013)
- Government of ACMS: By-laws 1987, 1 D (Box-folder 07-014)
- Grant: Optimization Models for Management Decision-Making 1977-82, 27 D (Box-folder 07-015)
  P.I. is Edward C. Wilson
- Grant: Experimental Medical Care Review Organization (EMCRO) 1971-75, 12 D (Box-folder 07-016)
  P.I. is James Respess
- Guide to Health Care 1985, 9 D (Box-folder 07-017)
  Included in the guide are instructions on how to choose a physician and a list of physicians.
- Health Care Task Force 1999, 6 D (Box-folder 07-018)
- Health Council of the community Improvement Council Board 1948-72, 58 D (Box-folder 07-019)
  Included topics are sewage disposal, well baby clinic in Crozet, visiting nurses, need for a Health Center for Charlottesville and Albemarle, Milk Ordinance, and fluoridation.
- Health Maintenance organization (HMO) 1978-81, 8 D (Box-folder 07-020)
- Instructive Visiting Nurses Association (IVNA) 1951-56, 4 D (Box-folder 07-021)
- Legislation 1958-75, 16 D (Box-folder 07-022)
  Includes letters regarding the Jenkins-Keough Bill signed by U.S. Representative Howard K. Smith, U.S. Senator A. Willis Robertson, and U.S. Senator Harry F. Byrd.
- Louisa Health Center for Young People 1982, 2 D (Box-folder 07-023)
- Martha Jefferson Hospital Education Liaison Fund 1979-84, 7 D (Box-folder 08-001)
- Measles Vaccination 1963, 2 D (Box-folder 08-002)
- Medical Examiners 1973-94, 23 D (Box-folder 08-003)
- Medical Malpractice Insurance 1968-91, 21 D (Box-folder 08-004)
- Medical Society of Virginia 1979, 4 D (Box-folder 08-005)
- Medical Student Participation 1969-71, 4 D (Box-folder 08-006)
- Medical Student Scholarship Fund 1976-82, 5 D (Box-folder 08-007)
- Membership 1953-98, 34 D (Box-folder 08-008)
- Membership Applications N.D., 8 D (Box-folder 08-009)
- Membership for House Staff 1950-91, 5 D (Box-folder 08-010)
- Newsletter 1988, 3 D (Box-folder 08-011)
- Officers 1965-2000, 9 D (Box-folder 08-012)
- Physician Fees pre 1965, 3 D (Box-folder 08-013)
- Picnic 1957-71, 14 D (Box-folder 08-014)
- Polio 1955-63, 116 D (Box-folder 08-015)
- Polio N.D., 8 D (Box-folder 08-016)
- Presidents' Photograph 1981 June 26, 1 D, 4.5 x 6.5 B&W Photo (Box-folder 08-017)
  This first known formal photograph of the ACMS presidents includes: Left to right, first row - Frank E. Taylor, 1980; Charles E. Hess, 1981; William B. Pollard, 1969; R. Gregory Magruder, 1949; G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, 1960; George R. Minor, 1967; W. Copley McLean, 1964; Wilmer H. Paine, 1936; White McK. Wallenborn, 1978; Harvey D. Smallwood, 1974. Left to right, second row - George D. Spence, 1976; Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., 1977; Edward P. Cawley, 1962; John L. Guerrant, 1965; Daniel N. Mohler, 1979; Armistead P. Booker, 1968; Harry L. Archer, 1955; Cary N. Moon, Jr., 1963; Morton C. Wilhelm, 1971.
- Questionnaires concerning ACMS 1993, 9 D (Box-folder 08-018)
- Resolutions 1944-91, 39 D (Box-folder 09-001)
  Includes resolutions about the Wagner Act, quarantine, firing of Dr. James Druff of Western State Hospital, mental illness, prescription drugs, compensation of physicians in teaching hospitals, trash, medical care for jail prisoners, ear-piercing, Emergency Medicine Services, health care insurance, and boxing.
- Resolution regarding establishment of regional medical programs 1965, 8 D (Box-folder 09-002)
  This resolution refers to H.R. bill Number 3140 also known as the Heart Disease, Cancer, and Stroke Amendments of 1965. Included are letters signed by U.S. Senator Harry F. Byrd, U.S. Senator A. Willis Robertson, and U.S. Representative Howard W. Smith.
- Resolution regarding optometrists and eye care 1977-81, 11 D (Box-folder 09-003)
- Resolution regarding school nurses 1991, 9 D (Box-folder 09-004)
- Resolution regarding tobacco use 1986-92, 6 D (Box-folder 09-005)
- Resolutions regarding traffic safety 1956-86, 31 D (Box-folder 09-006)
  Includes resolutions and correspondence about seat belts, alcohol use, child safety seats, and physical standards for the licensure of drivers. Includes letters signed by Virginia House of Delegates C. Armonde Paxson and Richard H. Middleton, and Virginia Senator Edward O. McCue.
- Resolution and Legislation: Forand Bill 1959-60, 15 D (Box-folder 09-007)
  ACMS opposes the Forand Bill which would provide certain health care services to social security recipients. Includes letters signed by Thomas J. Michie and Virginius Dabney; U.S. Representative Howard W. Smith; and U.S. Senators A. Willis Robertson, Harry F. Byrd, Lyndon B. Johnson, Huburt H. Humphrey, and John F. Kennedy.
- Resolutions of other organizations 1954-74, 12 D (Box-folder 09-008)
- Resolutions passed upon the death of a member, A-E 1968-82, 10 D (Box-folder 09-009)
  Archer, Vincent W.; Beckwith, Julian R.; Chapman, William Hardee
- Resolutions passed upon the death of a member, F-J 1968-85, 6 D (Box-folder 09-010)
  Fitz-Hugh, Glassell Slaughter; Hedges, Halstead Shipman
- Resolutions passed upon the death of a member, K-O 1954-90, 14 D (Box-folder 09-011)
  Leavell, Byrd Stuart; Lehman, Edwin P.; McCoy, H. Christopher; McGuire, Lockhart Bemiss; Mulholland, Henry Bearden
- Resolutions passed upon the death of a member, P-T 1966-89, 10 D (Box-folder 09-012)
  Rea, Montie Lewis; Sloop, Frank B.; Smith, Harry LeCato; Spaar, Albert Peter
- Resolutions passed upon the death of a member, U-Z 1965-82, 10 D (Box-folder 09-013)
  Wilson, David Cole; Wood, J. Edwin; Wood, William Hoge
- Southside Health Center, Scottsville 1983-85, 9 D (Box-folder 09-014)
- State Corporation Commission of Virginia 1951-2001, 78 D (Box-folder 09-015)
- Thomas Jefferson Emergency Medical Service Area 1984-89, 5 D (Box-folder 09-016)
- Veterans Administration 1945-48, 12 D (Box-folder 09-017)
- Virginia council on Health and Medical Care 1959-83, 24 D (Box-folder 09-018)
- Voluntary Medicare Assignment Program for Physicians (VMAPP) 1987-89, 6 D (Box-folder 09-019)
- Women's Auxiliary 1950-87, 37 D (Box-folder 09-020)
- Correspondence 1948, 5 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-001)
  Includes discussion concerning the invitation of African American physicians
- Correspondence 1950, 1 TL (Box-folder 10-002)
- Correspondence 1952, 1 TLS, 1 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-003)
  Includes A.M.A. Medical Education fund, blood replacement
- Correspondence 1953, 2 TL, 1 TL (Box-folder 10-004)
  Includes blood replacement, Blood Bank
- Correspondence 1956, 1 TLS (Box-folder 10-005)
- Correspondence 1957, 1 TLS, 1 TL, 1 newspaper clipping (Box-folder 10-006)
  Includes an advertisement in the newspaper by Wylie C. Mason
- Correspondence 1958, 7 TLS, 3 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-007)
  Includes AMA membership, African American membership, nursing homes
- Correspondence 1959, 13 TL, 12 TLS, 5 TD, 1 ANS, 1 brochure (Box-folder 10-008)
  Includes American Medical Education Fund, Virginia for Milk Freedom, blood replacement, Christmas presents, tuberculosis
- Correspondence 1960, 5TL, 8 TLS, 1 memo (Box-folder 10-009)
- Correspondence 1961, 9 TL, 10 TLS, 2 TD, 2ALS, 1 memo (Box-folder 10-010)
  Includes employment of handicapped, civil defense and Albemarle Resuce Squad
- Correspondence 1962, 3 TL, 1 TLS, 1 TLS with AN (Box-folder 10-011)
- Correspondence 1963, 1 TL, 1 TLS (Box-folder 10-012)
- Correspondence 1964, 1 TL, 1 TLS (Box-folder 10-013)
  Includes Rescue Squad calls being listed in newspaper and request for patient anonymity
- Correspondence 1965, 4 TL, 9 TLS, 3 TD, 1 TDS, 1 ALS (Box-folder 10-014)
  Includes meningitis, regular check-ups, hearing, Medic Alert, Head Start program, Eldercare vs. Medicare, UVa Mental Health Clinic and lunacy hearings. The Head Start letter is signed by Sargent Shriver.
- Correspondence 1966, 9 TL, 3 TLS, 1 business card (Box-folder 10-015)
  Includes Medic Alert, meningitis, venereal diseases
- Correspondence 1967, 1 TL, 1 TLS (Box-folder 10-016)
- Correspondence 1968, 1 TL, 1 TL with ANS, 1 TDS (Box-folder 10-017)
  Includes nursing home care, employment of first permanent secretary for the ACMS: Betty Finn suggested
- Correspondence 1970, 1 TL, 2 newspaper clippings (Box-folder 10-018)
  Includes house staff payment
- Correspondence 1971, 3 TL, 6 TLS, 1 TLS with AN (Box-folder 10-019)
- Correspondence 1972, 1 TL, 7 TLS (Box-folder 10-020)
  Includes emergency medical services, Sports Medicine Committee
- Correspondence 1973, 2 TL, 12 TLS (Box-folder 10-021)
  Includes emergency medical services, Charlottesville Albemarle Rescue Squad
- Correspondence 1974, 3 TLl, 3 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-022)
  Includes Civil Rights Act, staffing at Blue Ridge Sanatorium
- Correspondence 1975, 3 TL, 5 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-023)
  Includes flu vaccine, Health System Agency
- Correspondence [1976], 1 TL (Box-folder 10-024)
- Correspondence 1977, 6 TL, 2 TLS, 1 ALS (Box-folder 10-025)
  Includes Professional Standards Review Organization (PSRO)
- Correspondence 1978, 2 TL, 5 TLS, 2 TD (Box-folder 10-026)
- Correspondence 1979, e TLS (Box-folder 10-027)
- Correspondence 1980, 1 TLS, 2 TD (Box-folder 10-028)
- Correspondence 1981, 1 TL, 2 TD, 1 postcard (Box-folder 10-029)
- Correspondence 1982, 3 TL, 7 TLS, 1 TLS with AN, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-030)
- Correspondence 1983, 4TL, 5 TLS, 3 TD, 1 memo, 1 postcard (Box-folder 10-031)
  Includes UVa replacement hospital
- Correspondence 1984, 1 TL, 1 note, 2 memos, 1 newspaper clipping (Box-folder 10-032)
- Correspondence 1985, 2 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-033)
- Correspondence 1986, 1 TLS (Box-folder 10-034)
  Includes committee to involve women in ACMS
- Correspondence 1987, 2 TL, 2 TLS (Box-folder 10-035)
- Correspondence 1988, 6 TLS, 1 memo (Box-folder 10-036)
  Includes letters objecting to use of Farmington Country Club as a meeting locale because of FCC's policy concerning minorities and religions
- Correspondence 1989, 1 TL, 6 TLS, 2 TD, 2 memos (Box-folder 10-037)
  Includes ophthalmologists and optometrists, osteopathic physicians, Health Behaviors in Planning District 10
- Correspondence 1990, 5 TL, 4 TLS (Box-folder 10-038)
- Correspondence 1991, 1 TL, 6 TLS, 1 TD, 1 memo (Box-folder 10-039)
- Correspondence 1992, 3 TL, 20 TLS, 1 TLS with AN, 1 memo, 2 ALS, 5 TD (Box-folder 10-040)
  Includes smoking, cigarette tax
- Correspondence 1993, 1 TL, 3 TLS, 1 ALS (Box-folder 10-041)
- Correspondence 1994, 4 TLS (Box-folder 10-042)
- Correspondence 1995, 4 TLS (Box-folder 10-043)
- Correspondence 1997, 3 TL, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 10-044)
- Correspondence 1998, 4 TL, 5 TLS, 3 TD, 1 ALS (Box-folder 10-045)
- Correspondence 1999, 1 TLS, 1 TD with AN, 2 emails (Box-folder 10-046)
- Correspondence 2000, 3 TLS, 1 TD, 1 email (Box-folder 10-047)
- Correspondence 2001, 9 TL, 6 TLS, 2 TD, 2 memos, 12 emails (Box-folder 10-048)
- Correspondence 2002, 1 TL, 4 emails (Box-folder 10-049)
- Minutes [1951], 1 TD (Box-folder 11-001)
  Initial meeting of the incorporation and members of the ACMS
- Minutes 1965, 1 TD (Box-folder 11-002)
- Minutes 1971, 1 TD (Box-folder 11-003)
- Minutes 1980, 17 TD (Box-folder 11-004)
- Minutes 1981, 19 TD (Box-folder 11-005)
- Minutes 1982, 16 TD (Box-folder 11-006)
- Minutes 1983, 16 TD (Box-folder 11-007)
- Minutes 1984, 18TD (Box-folder 11-008)
- Minutes 1985, 18 TD (Box-folder 11-009)
- Minutes 1986, 9 TD (Box-folder 11-010)
- Minutes 1987, 12 TD (Box-folder 11-011)
- Minutes 1988, 18 TD (Box-folder 11-012)
- Minutes 1989, 19 TD (Box-folder 11-013)
- Minutes 1990, 19 TD (Box-folder 11-014)
- Minutes, Agenda 1991, 19 TD (Box-folder 11-015)
- Minutes, Agenda 1992, 22 TD (Box-folder 11-016)
- Minutes, Agendas 1993, 25 TD (Box-folder 11-017)
- Minutes, Agendas 1994, 25 TD (Box-folder 11-018)
- Minutes 1995, 18 TD (Box-folder 11-019)
- Agendas 1996, 2 TD (Box-folder 11-020)
- Minutes, Agendas, Memoranda 1998, 30 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 11-021)
- Minutes 1999, 10 TD (Box-folder 11-022)
- Agendas, Financial reports 2000, 9 TD (Box-folder 11-023)
- Agendas 2001, 2 TD (Box-folder 11-024)
- Financial ledgers March 2, 1933-October 29, 1942; January 20, 1944-January 7, 1947, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-001)
- Financial ledgers March 11, 1947-January 7, 1952; February 7, 1952-January 31, 1957, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-002)
- Financial ledgers February 7, 1957-October 6, 1960; October 13, 1960-December 5, 1963, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-003)
- Financial ledgers December 5, 1963-November 10, 1966, November 28, 1966-December 5, 1968, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-004)
- Financial ledgers December 12, 1968-June 11, 1971; June 17, 1971-April 1, 1974, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-005)
- Financial ledgers April 1, 1974-September 17, 1976; September 27, 1976-January 8, 1979, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 12-006)
- Financial ledgers January 24, 1979-June 3, 1981; June 15, 1981-August 4, 1983, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 13-001)
- Financial ledgers August 5, 1983-June 26, 1985; June 26, 1985-October 15, 1987, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 13-002)
- Financial ledgers November 9, 1987-October 1, 1990; October 1, 1990-October 14, 1992, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 13-003)
- Financial ledgers Ocotber 14, 1992-March 10, 1994; December 17, 1997-November 17, 1999, 2 financial ledgers (Box-folder 13-004)
- Financial ledger January 1977-December 1985, financial ledger (Box-folder 13-005)
- Adjusting journal entries 1982-84, 3 AD (Box-folder 13-006)
- Financial transaction register February 26, 1990-December 21, 1992, 1 D with AN (Box-folder 13-007)
- Financial ledger 1999-2000, 1 AD (Box-folder 13-008)
- Finances, 1952 1953, 4 TLS (Box-folder 14-001)
- Finances, 1952, 53 1954, 1 TLS, 2 TD (Box-folder 14-002)
- Finances, 1954 1955, 1 TL, 1 TLS, 2 TD (Box-folder 14-003)
- Finances, 1955 1956, 1 TL, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-004)
- Finances, 1956 1957, 1 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-005)
- Finances, 1957 1958, 1 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-006)
- Finances, 1958 [1959], 1 TD with ANs (Box-folder 14-007)
- Finances, 1959 1960, 1 TL, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-008)
- Finances, 1960 1961, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-009)
- Finances, 1961 1962, 1 TL, 2 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-010)
- Finances, 1962 [1963], 1 TD (Box-folder 14-011)
- Finances, 1963 [1964], 1 TD (Box-folder 14-012)
- Finances, 1964 [1965], 1 TD (Box-folder 14-013)
- Finances, 1965 1965-66, 2 TDS, 1 TLS (Box-folder 14-014)
- Finances, 1966 [1967], 2 TD (Box-folder 14-015)
- Finances, 1967 1968, 1 TNS with ANS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-016)
- Finances, 1968 [1969], 1 TD (Box-folder 14-017)
- Finances, 1969 1970, 2 TNS, 2 TD (Box-folder 14-018)
- Finances, 1970 [1971], 2 TD (Box-folder 14-019)
- Finances, 1971 1972, 2 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-020)
- Finances, 1972 1973, 2 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-021)
- Finances, 1973 1973-74, 2 TLS, 2 TL, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-022)
- Finances, 1974 1975, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-023)
- Finances, 1975 1976, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-024)
- Finances, 1976 [1977], 1 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-025)
- Finances, 1977 [1978], 1 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-026)
- Finances, 1978 1979, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-027)
- Finances, 1980 [1981], 1 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-028)
- Finances, 1981 1982, 1 TL, 1 TLS, 3 TD (Box-folder 14-029)
- Finances, 1983 1984, 2 TLS, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-030)
- Finances, 1984 1984-[1985], 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-031)
- Finances, 1984-85 1985, 3 TD, 1 TLS with AN, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-032)
- Finances, 1985-86 1986, 2 TD, 1 TL, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-033)
- Finances, 1986-87 1987, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-034)
- Finances, 1987-88 1988, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-035)
- Finances, 1988-89 1989, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-036)
- Finances, 1989-90 1990, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-037)
- Finances, 1990-91 1991, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-038)
- Finances, 1991-92 1992, 1 TLS, 2 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-039)
- Finances, 1992-93 1993, 2 TLS, 3 TD (Box-folder 14-040)
- Finances, 1993-94 1994-95, 3 TLS, 6 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-041)
- Finances, 1994-95 1995, 3 TLS, 3 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 14-042)
- Finances, 1995-96 1996-97, 5 TLS, 6 TD, 2 TD with AN (Box-folder 14-043)
- Finances, 1996-97 1997, 4 TLS, 3 TD (Box-folder 14-044)
- Finances, 1997-98 1998, 3 TLS, 2 TD, 1 email, 1 memo (Box-folder 14-045)
- Finances, 1998-99 1999, 2 TLS, 1 TL, 2 TD (Box-folder 14-046)
- Finances, 2000-01 2002, 1 TLS, 1 TD (Box-folder 14-047)